Finding Aid for Floyd Starr papers, 1933-1970
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Floyd Starr papers 1933-1970
Starr, Floyd Elliot, 1883-1980.
4 microfilm s and 2 folders
85403 mf 539c-mf 542c; UAs, UAm
Founder and president of the Starr Commonwealth for Boys in Albion, Michigan. The scrapbooks contain clippings, articles, and other printed matter relating to the work of Starr Commonwealth and the activities of its boys. There are also scattered original photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The scrapbooks were made available for microfilming by Floyd Starr and the Starr Commonwealth for Boys (donor no. 505 ).
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Floyd Starr was the founder and president of the Starr Commonwealth for Boys in Albion, Michigan. Born in Decatur, Michigan, on May 1, 1883, Starr graduated from Marshall High School, then worked for several years in a half-way house in St. Louis, Missouri. He returned to Michigan where he attended Albion College, receiving his Bachelor of Arts degree in 1910. He was employed for a brief time at the Bernarr McFadden's Healthatorium in Chicago. He then went to work at the Beulah Home for Boys. With a burden for delinquent, homeless, and neglected boys, Starr had hopes of establishing his own nonprofit home and residential school for these boys. In 1913, he was able to purchase forty acres of land on Montcalm Lake. From this beginning developed the Starr Commonwealth for Boys which Starr guided for more than fifty years as president. He retired from active administrative responsibilities in 1967, but continued to provide guidance until his death on August 27, 1980, at the age of 97.
The Floyd Starr scrapbooks were microfilmed in 1978 with the permission of Starr Commonwealth for Boys (SCB). After filming was completed the books were returned to Starr Commonwealth. The scrapbooks were microfilmed selectively, approximately ninety-five percent of the original material finding its way into this microfilm edition.
The scrapbooks were divided into three series for filming. The first series -- Floyd Starr Scrapbooks - consisted of twelve books containing material created between 1933 and 1963, as well as one additional book of fundraising material dated from 1958 to 1970. Arranged chronologically, this series was created as a conscious attempt to preserve the history of SCB, and the people associated with it. It ranges broadly in subject and type of material. The school itself, Floyd Starr personally, former students, staff members, benefactors, and even persons who at one time spent a few days at SCB are all subjects for inclusion. Newspaper clippings are the most common type of material found, but mimeographed material, photographs, manuscript items and even autographs all have found their way into these volumes.
A second series consists almost exclusively of newspaper articles written about Starr Commonwealth by Myrtle B. Brown, covering the years 1948 to 1962. Brown, in charge of the school's public relations department, was responsible for writing a weekly column for the Albion Evening Recorder describing activities at SCB.
Within the miscellaneous scrapbooks series, there is a volume created for the school's 35th anniversary in 1948. The other two volumes, covering the years 1947 to 1955, seem to have been maintained by the school's Women's Auxiliary. The group's function was fundraising, primarily by means of benefit fashion shows. Most of the material contained in these two books duplicates information found in the Floyd Starr series.
The collection also includes a few original items, mainly scattered photographs of Starr alone or with some of the Starr Commonwealth boys. There is also a mounted time-line of Starr Commonwealth history located in the Starr Room of the Bentley Historical Library.
Subjects:
Albion (Calhoun County, Mich.); Starr Commonwealth for Boys.; Starr, Floyd Elliot, 1883-1980
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Children--Michigan--Health and welfare.; Starr Commonwealth for Boys.; Starr, Floyd Elliot, 1883-1980
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Floyd Starr Scrapbooks
  - 1933-1935 (Reel 1)
  - 1936-1942 (Reel 1)
  - 1943-1949 (Reel 1)
  - 1950-1952 (Reel 2)
  - 1953 (Reel 2)
  - 1954-1956 (Reel 2)
  - 1957 (Reel 3)
  - 1958 (Reel 3)
  - 1959 (Reel 3)
  - 1960 (Reel 3)
  - 1961-1962 (Reel 3)
  - 1963 (Reel 4)
  - Fundraising material, 1958-1963, 1970 (Reel 4)
- Myrtle B. Brown Scrapbooks
  - 1948-1955 (Reel 4)
  - November 1955-1958 (Reel 4)
  - 1959-196o (Reel 4)
  - 1961-1962 (Reel 4)
- Miscellaneous Scrapbooks
  - 35th Anniversary, 1948 (Reel 4)
  - 1947-1953 (Reel 4)
  - 1954-1955 (Reel 4)
- Photographs
  - Portraits and photos of Starr with boys at the Starr Commonwealth (Folder UAs/UAm)
    (In the Floyd Starr memorial room of the Bentley Historical Library, there are additional Starr related photographs)
Related Material
The original Starr scrapbooks and other materials are available at the Starr Commonwealth Archives in Albion, Michigan.